Curriculum Vitae

Name: Williams Njoku

Telephone: 0892435836 E-Mail: w_njoku@hotmail.com

Career Aim: I have been privileged to work with multinational companies on an international level, furthermore, I have been able to gain experience within various sectors of Occupational Health and safety. Each time, I bring my gained experiences and expertise into each company. My competence in my role keeps creating opportunities for corporate and personal growth.

Employment

March 2023 - Present

Job Title: Project EHS Lead, Dornan Engineering Ltd, Ireland (Google Data Centre, Belgium).

Duties:

- Managing day-to-day EHS duties for Dornan Engineering Ltd as the GC (General Contractor)
- Liaison between Dornan Engineering and Client (Google)

August 2022 - March 2023

Job Title: Senior Project EHS Adviser, Dornan Engineering Ltd, Ireland (Facebook Cloonee & MSD Dunboyne).

Duties:

- Played the role of PSCS on site where client entrusted project EHS roles for me to manage
- Responsible for implementation and management of environmental health and safety policies and protocols
- Experience in Mobilizing commitment among all contractor and subcontractors on site with the focus on achieving environmental health and safety targets
- Project environmental health and safety adviser in the construction phase of CLN 5 and CLN 6
 Facebook data centre facility (300m)
- Project environmental health and safety adviser in the construction of MSD BioNX research project (450m)
- Involved in EHS meetings and walk-through site with main contractor's representatives
- Played a key role in managing client (PM Group) and Dornan Engineering Ltd trade partners with regards to environmental health and safety matters
- Review and signed safe plan action (SPA) of subcontractors on site
- Played the role of EHS liaison between main contractor and Dornan Engineering Ltd to ensure main contractor's standards are upheld by Dornan Eng. Ltd employees/subcontractors on site
- Fully trained manual handling instructor
- Involved in and completed site senior leadership team (SLT) and Dornan Eng. Ltd audits
- In charge of site inductions and ensuring PPE were provided to new and old employees
- Responsible for site toolbox talk among Dornan Eng. Ltd employees and subcontractors
- Member of project First Aiders on site

March 2021 - July 2022

Job Title: Senior Environmental Health and Safety Adviser, OHLA Group, Ireland. (€210m & €70m)

Duties:

• Environmental Health and Safety Lead for a PSCS company

- Responsible for implementation and management of environmental health and safety policies and protocols
- Health & Safety Lead and Manager over two major sites with employees of over 200 staff (subcontractors and contractors) in a JV social housing PPP bundle 2 (Dublin, Kildare and Waterford)
 [230m]
- Health & Safety Lead for a construction of PPP higher education TU Dublin Academic Hub and Library Complex [70m]
- Responsible for liaison with Management and engaging respective stakeholders within the Joint Venture (JV) team with respect to environmental health and safety issues on all sites
- Solely responsible in the management of accident- incident management control of particular sites prone to incidences- successful at greatly reducing the rate of incidence or accidents
- Support on delivering and completing statutory notifications to the HSA as necessary.
- Ensuring sub-contractor documentation and training has been reviewed prior to commencement and complies with legal and company policies.
- Liaise closely with the Construction team to coordinate issues relating to the Site e.g., waste disposal, W@H, fire safety equipment, Site logistics and other compliance testing and audit non-compliances.
- Safety lead responsible in designing and implementing health and safety management programs as well as carrying our audit with the aim to reduce near misses and accidents
- Fully trained on and site Manual Handling Instructor
- Safety Lead responsible in the design and implementation of site toolbox talk with contractors, subcontractors, and site visitors on both sites
- Coordinated and chaired health and safety meetings on all sites as required (usually 1-2ce weekly)
- Responsible for team building amongst all ground staff with aim to promote a positive health and safety culture – 'Safety conscious awareness sessions'
- Responsible in ensuring the implementation of Covid-19 precautionary measures on site and full cooperation of all subcontractors and site management team
- Reported to operational director and project director with regards to health and safety matters
- Collecting and collating relevant information for inclusion in the Safety File and preparing for handover to the Client at the end of the project.
- Involved in whiteboard meetings with subcontractors and site management team on both sites
- Played a key role as public liaison between ROHL Ltd and the public with regards to environmental health and safety matters
- Safety lead and sole Responsible in the conduction of health and safety compliance audits- with aim to increase awareness and promote a safe work environment follow through with corrective actions
- Responsible in the implementation of ISO 45001, 14001 and 9001
- Responsible in collating all statutory forms (GA1, GA2, GA3, Hot Works Permit, Permit to Dig etc.)
- First Aid trained and responsible in reporting to HSA where injured party is absent for more than 3days
- Responsible on investigating accidents, incidents, high potential near misses or other significant events/issues. Ensuring that investigation close out action's plans are completed in the required time frame.
- Responsible in reporting accidents, completing AF2 forms to Health and safety Authority
- Responsible and reviewed PSCS and subcontractors Risk Assessment Method Statement (RAMS) and completed Safe System of Work Plan (SSWP) in conjunction with subcontractor's site team
- Prepared, updated and delivered health and safety induction on multiple sites
- Responsible in employees training needs, records and ensuring level of competency are attained

July 2020 - February 2021

Job Title: Senior Environmental Health and Safety Adviser, SMG Formwork Ltd, BAM Contractors Ltd.

Duties:

- Senior environmental health and safety for a PSCS.
- Responsible for implementation and auditing of environmental health and safety matters at INTEL, Kildare (9 billion+)
- Managing the day-to-day operational safety management of all 170 employees of SMG Formwork Ltd.

- Ensured the adequate interpretation and conveying environmental health and safety guidelines to foreign nationals.
- Ensuring that all employees adhere to all COVID-19 precautionary measures.
- Liaising with Tier 1 contractors on environmental health and safety matters on site.
- First aid trained and member of onsite first aiders.
- Managed and responded to complaints and other safety feedback from employees.
- Member of the Construction Incident Response Team (CIRT) on site.
- On site Train the Trainer incident free workplace training.
- Responsible for weekly toolbox meetings.
- Responsible in ensuring workers training certificates/records were up to date.
- Responsible for communicating risk and method statements/safe system of work plan, safety statement and permits to work (PTW) to all employees.
- Responsible for incident/accident reporting on site and to the Health and Safety Authority.
- Reporting directly to the CEO of the company concerning environmental health and safety matters.
- Responsible for delivering induction trainings to new employees.
- Ability to think innovatively and create initiatives that utilises resources optimally.
- Experienced at addressing communication issues as well as promoting communication to improve the work environment.

May 2019 - June 2020:

Job Title: Environmental Health and Safety Adviser, SIAC Construction, Ireland.

Duties:

- Environmental health and safety Adviser for a PSCS
- Responsible for implementation and auditing of environmental health and safety matters at two projects in West of Ireland (Sligo Road construction and Ballinasloe water services upgrade) (34m & 24m).
- Managing the day-to-day operational safety management of staff assigned to the two sites (Sligo and Ballinasloe).
- Ensure safe delivery of services with compliance to infection control standards and national guidelines for the prevention of the spread of COVID-19.
- Ensuring the effective, efficient and safety measures of subcontractors and visitors on both construction sites.
- Ensuring timely access of subcontractors to the construction site by conducting inductions with respect to their assigned duties.
- Responsible and ensuring the ordering and delivery of appropriate COVID -19 infection control equipment e.g. gloves, alcohol wipes, facemasks where appropriate
- Responsible for site team environmental health and safety inspection for both sites.
- Managing teams through the conduction of toolbox talk on safety measures on the site.
- Actively involved in the implementation of COVID-19 precautionary measures for all staff members and sub-contractors on site.
- Responsible for daily briefing to staff to maintain and improve their compliance with respect to COVID-19 national guidelines.
- Monitor and report safety performance indicators, such as Safety Health and Environmental (SHE) reports to the senior managements.
- Partook in progress meetings with both clients and sub-contractors to discuss safety issues that may be of concern on site.
- Managed and responded to complaints and other safety feedback from employees and subcontractors in accordance to SIAC environmental health and safety policies.
- Responsible and participated in the review of safety statements and method statements for SIAC and sub-contractors.
- Ability to manage competing demands and tight deadlines whilst consistently marinating high standards and positive working relationships.
- Manage and ensure the compliance of all components of quality assurance systems (ISO 9001); risk management, incident reporting etc.

- Responsible in ensuring the implementation of all SIAC environmental health and safety policies, procedures and standards to ensure staff wellbeing.
- Creating and maintaining links with both internal and external stakeholders to ensure that appropriate pathways are developed with respect to environmental health and safety on site.
- Collaborating with the conservative officers with respect to protective species around site premises.
- Created an initiative on enhancing staff mental health and well-being.
- Responsible for collection and updating HSA forms such as GA1, GA2, GA3 and AF3.
- Ensuring that all environmental health and safety related records are maintained and available for audits.
- Responsible for recording all incident reports as well as investigations in accordance with both SIAC and HSA procedures.
- Graduate member of Institute of Occupational Safety.
- Ability to critically analyse environmental safety and health procedures and make necessary readjustments and changes to improve safety on our sites.
- Possess the ability to negotiate and discuss necessary plans with involving stakeholders to ensure safe and successful implementation of the necessary plans/tasks/policies.
- Experienced in safety and health audits.
- Participated and ensured traffic management plans are in place on both sites.
- Experienced in mentoring and encouraging good safety culture among employees and subcontractors on both sites.
- I am emotionally intelligent and use this ability to support individuals and the teams I may find myself in through the course of providing health and safety at workplace.

October 2017 - May 2019:

Job Title: Supervisor, Ivy Hotel Castlebar, Co. Mayo, Ireland.

Duties:

- Responsible for addressing and managing environmental health and safety issues in the hotel (48 suites).
- Responsible for ensuring that all fire exits, fire extinguishers comply with HSA guideline.
- Responsible for giving toolbox talks to all staffs.
- Responsible and ensuring that all staffs are trained, and training records are kept up-to-date.
- Responsible in carrying out investigations, accident, incident, near misses and filing out reports.
- Assisted in the preparation of company safety statement and risk assessment.
- Responsible for the implementation of health and safety measures during private events.
- Responsible in accident, incident and near-misses reporting.

January 2015 - April 2017

Job Title: Site Safety Adviser/Occupational First Aid 3 at Quorum Construction Group, Vancouver, BC., Canada.

Duties:

- Responsible for the day-to-day Safety issues in the construction of a high-rise (22 floors).
- Responsible and conducted toolbox meetings with all staffs on site.
- Designed and responsible for conducting orientations on site (305 employees).
- Responsible and gave inductions to new workers on site.
- Trained and responsible as a first responder Level 3 first aid to attended to injured workers on site.
- Responsible and managed staffs on site while superintendent was away.
- Managed and responsible in dealing with near misses, incident, accident reports.
- Responsible in ensuring workers training certificates/records were up to date.

January 2011 - October 2014

Job Title: Site Safety Officer/Occupational First Aid 3 at Urban One, Vancouver, BC., Canada.

Duties:

- Played a key role as a team safety personnel for construction of Donald Trump Tower (70 floors).
- Engaged and responsible for incident, near misses, accident reports on site.
- Trained and responsible as a first responder Level 3 first aid to attended to injured workers on site.
- Responsible in giving inductions to new and old workers (625 employees).
- Responsible and conducted toolbox meetings with all staffs on site.
- Liaised with internal and external stakeholders concerning safety issues on site.
- Played a key role in safety audits and liaising with external auditors to ensure company compliance with Canadian Centre for Occupational Health and Safety (CCOHS).

August 2004 - November 2010

Job Title: Manager at Doolins Irish Pub, Vancouver, BC., Canada.

Duties:

- Responsible for giving Induction/orientation to new workers.
- Supervised the compliance of health and safety policies within the organisation.
- Managed, prioritise, organise and schedule a wide variety of tasks.
- Responsible for investigating, monitoring, completing Incident and near miss report.
- Managed and responsible for 30 staffs.
- Responsible and in charge of quality control for the organisation.
- Responsible and managed Payroll for staffs.
- Provided leadership to ensure a multi-disciplinary approach to facilitate working groups within the organisation.

Education:

2021 (July) FETAC Level 6 Manual Handling Instructor

2020 - 2022 M.Sc. Environmental Health and Safety Management

Institute of Technology, Sligo, Republic of Ireland

2020 (June) Certificate in Training and Development

Institute of Technology, Sligo, Republic of Ireland

2020 (May-June) Certificate in Lean Sigma Quality

Institute of Technology, Sligo, Republic of Ireland

2019 - 2020 B.Sc. (Hons) Occupational Safety & Health

Institute of Technology, Sligo, Republic of Ireland

2018 - 2019 B.Sc. Occupational Safety & Health

Institute of Technology, Sligo, Republic of Ireland

2017 - 2018 Certificate in Environmental and Occupational Health & Safety

University of Victoria, BC, Canada

2017 Certificate in Safety and Health

Institute of Technology, Sligo, Republic of Ireland

2016 Construction Safety Specialist

BC Construction Safety Alliance, New Westminster, BC, Canada

2015 National Construction Safety Officer

Alberta Construction Safety Association, Edmonton, AB, Canada

2014 B.Sc. General Studies

University of Fraser Valley, Abbotsford, BC, Canada

2009 Diploma in Criminology

Douglas College, New Westminster, BC, Canada

Examination Awarded: West African Examination Council

Subjects completed: Maths, English, Home Economics, Biology, Physics, Chemistry and Business Studies.

Skills and Awards:

- Irish citizenship
- Full Irish driver's licence.
- Fluent in reading and written English.
- Graduate member of **IOSH** (Institute of Occupational Safety and Health).
- Manual handling training.
- Hard working, self-motivated, willing to learn, responsible, reliable and flexible.
- Interpretation and application of EHS legislation, guidelines and codes.

Achievements:

- Volunteered with Castlebar Christian fellowship in Co. Mayo to deliver health and safety advice and address fire extinguishers, fire exits issues.
- Volunteered and completed safety statement for the Physiotherapy department in Mayo University Hospital.
- Participated in compiling required documents to meet KN *Circet* ISO 45001, 14001 certifications.

Hobbies and Interests:

- Table tennis
- Basketball
- Soccer

References

Upon request.